Nicole: So how do the ISO
standards support cyber security?
A cyber security professional will
probably find the ISO/IEC 27001 standard
details most of the requirements
that a business needs to follow to
comply with ISO 27000 standards.
Abraham: It sets out the
specifications that an Information
Security Management System [ISMS]
must meet to become certified.
An ISMS is the set of policies and
procedures including legal, physical
and technical controls involved in the
information risk management process.
Nicole: Those organisations that
meet the standards can become
certified as ISO 27001 compliant by
an accredited certification body.
Abraham: ISO 27001
requires organisations to:
• Systematically examine information
security risks looking at threats,
vulnerabilities and impact.
• Design and implement security controls
to address unacceptable risks.
• Develop a comprehensive management process
to regularly review and update the ISMS
taking into consideration the threat
environment and other developments.
Nicole: The ISO 27001 also includes
guidelines for developing controls
in a range of areas such as
information security policies, human
resource security, asset management,
operations and communications security
and compliance amongst others.
Abraham: By aligning an organisations
ISMS to the ISO 27001 standard it
can also help to show that measures
have been taken to comply with GDPR.
Nicole: In the event of a data breach
happening an ISMS that conforms to ISO
27001 will demonstrate to the regulator
that they have done all they can to
prevent and recover from an attack.
Abraham: The ISO 27032 standard is
usually used together with ISO 27001 and
includes guidelines on information and
data protection to make sure there are no
gaps in security policies and procedures
Nicole: It focuses on information systems
and guidelines to prevent data leaks,
like encrypting communication channels.
The emphasis is more on network
and internet security and critical
information infrastructure.
Abraham: The ISO 27000 family as we
have said covers a range of different
standards that can help organisations
to develop different aspects of their
security controls and ISMS systems.
Nicole: ISO standards provide best
practice guidance so having ISO 27000
certification can help organisations
to show that they use effective
security practices and procedures.
This can in turn give employees
and clients assurance that
their data is in safe hands.
Abraham: Some organisations will
also have to show that they are ISO
certified as a condition of doing
business, this is especially true
when working with government bodies.